Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  - BYRON, GEORGE GORDON NOEL BYRON, 6TH BAR. 1788-1824
    - ALS: Villa Dupuis, Pisa, to Mrs. Catherine Potter Stith, 1822 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      2 p.; 20 cm.
      Printed in Benson, Adolph B., Catherine
      Accompanying the gift to Mrs. Stith of
      F. A. M. Retzsch's Outlines to
      Goethe's Faust.
  - C., F.
    - Autograph poem without title, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
      4 l.
      Unsigned, but in same handwriting as
      "Schiller Prolog," which is signed:
      F. C.
      With envelope "Department of the
      Interior, Bureau of Pensions, The
      Commissioner of Pensions,
      Washington, D.C."
      Noted on envelope: Prolog zur Faust
      Feier, April 30, 1908.
      First line: Erhab'ner Geist, im
      Geisterreich verloren.
    - Autograph poem, "Schiller Prolog", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Signed: F. C.
      Noted on envelope: May 4, 1905
      May 7, 1905; Nov. 13, 1909
      Nov. 10, 1912.
      A laudatory poem.
  - CARLYLE, THOMAS, 1795-1881
    - ALS to "Dear Sir", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
      2 p.; 10 x 10 cm.
      Apparently accompanying some
      corrected data on Carlyle's life.
      The note ends: "Besides have we not
      eight translations of Faust
      already? And it is the most
      insignificant work I think (except
      Werter) that bears the great
      Goethe's name."
    - ALS: Craigenputtock, to "Dear Sir", 1830 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      1 p.; 13 x 19 cm.
      Concerns his opinion of Friedrich
      von Schiller.
    - ALS: Chelsea, London, to "My Dear Sir", 1834 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      2 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Letter discusses Ms. about the second
      part of Faust written by the brother
      of recipient.
      Letter from the publisher, Fraser,
      mentioned as being enclosed, is not
      present.
    - ALS: Chelsea, London, to "My Dear Sir", 1844 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      3 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Letter of appreciation for the mask
      of Goethe, which the recipient had
      sent to Carlyle.
      Printed in: Schreiber, Carl F.,
      Carlyle's Goethe Mask, in: Yale
      Library Gazette, 18 (1943): 26-29.
    - ALS: Chelsea, to Freiherr Christian Karl Josias von Bunsen, 1847 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - ALS: Chelsea, to Freiherr Christian Karl Josias von Bunsen, 1848 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - ALS: Craigenputtock, Dumfries, to John George Cochrane, 1831 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      3 p.; 19 x 23 cm.
    - ALS: Chelsea, to John Sullivan Dwight, 1838 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - ALS: Dumfries, Scotland, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1828 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      4 p.; 20 x 25 cm.
      Published in: Speck, William A.
      "New letters of Carlyle
      to Eckermann," Yale Review,
      July 1926.
      Subsequent letters from Carlyle to
      Eckermann were published in same
      source as above.
    - ALS: Craigenputtock, Dumfries, Scotland, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1834 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - ALS: Chelsea, London, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1837 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      4 p.; 19 x 23 cm.
    - ALS: Chelsea, London, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1845 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - ALS: Chelsea, London, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1848 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - AL (fragment): Chelsea, London, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1848 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      The last part of the letter has
      apparently been lost.
    - ALS: Chelsea, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1849 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - ALS: Mainhill, to John Ferguson, 1821 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - ALS: Birmingham, to J. Hessey, 1824 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      2 p.; 16 x 22 cm.
      Concerns the publication of Carlyle's
      The Life of Friedrich Schiller.
      Postscript: "Make my compliments to
      Mr. Taylor and...inform him...that
      Wilhelm Meisters Travels will not
      do. It is full of genius: but in a
      state of a fragment, and unfit for
      the English market."
    - ALS: Mainhill, Scotland, to Nikolaus Heinrich Julius, 1826 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 59)
      With personal red seal attached.
      Concerns chiefly Carlyle's work on
      German romance: Specimens of its
      chief authors, 1827, 4 v. Appeals
      to Dr. Julius to forward from
      Hamburg some books, which Carlyle
      needs to complete the compilation
      of this work.
    - ALS: Edinburgh, to Nikolaus Heinrich Julius?, 1826 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      Thanking him for the books shipped
      through Mr. Aiken; discussion of
      Carlyle's work, German romance:
      Specimens of its chief authors,
      1827, 4 v.
    - ALS: Edinburgh, to Nikolaus Heinrich Julius?, 1827 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - ALS: Edinburgh, to Bryan Waller Procter, 1828 Jan 17 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Proctor wrote under the pen name of
      Barry Cornwall.
    - Printed card, signed "T. Carlyle" and numbered "184" (Box 1, Folder 63)
      1 p.; 7 x 11 cm.
      Admitting bearer to "Mr. Carlyle's
      Lectures On the History of
      Literature [London, April-June
      1838], 17 Edwards Street, Portman
      Square ... at Three o'Clock
      precisely."
  - CARUS, CARL GUSTAV, 1789-1869
    - Lebenserinnerungen und Denkwürdigkeiten ... Fünfter Teil (fragment) (Box 2, Folder 64)
      Typescript (carbon), 4 p. l.,
      59 numb l., 1 l., 60-117 numb. l.,
      1 l., 118-174 numb. l., 1 l.,
      175-184 numb. l.; 14 x 22 cm. in
      binder.
      Contents: Anknüpfungen; Fortgesetzte
      und erneute Tätigkeit; Bedeutende
      Individualitäten; Autorenleben,
      Krieg.
    - Parallele zwischen Faust Göthe's und dem wunderthätigen Magus Calderon's (Box 2, Folder 65)
      AMs, 1 p. l., 24 p.; 23 x 28 cm.
      In board covers.
      Dedicatory inscription on preliminary
      leaf: Zur Erinnerung an A.[?] G.
      Carus seinem verehrten Freunde
      Schwender. d. 1/xii 73.
      Apparently written in preparation for
      the printer, judging from a pencil
      note in the margin: Nb Hier mehr
      Raum lassen.
      With typed copy.
  - CHARLES FREDERICK, GRAND DUKE OF BADEN, 1728-1811
    - LS, to unnamed cousin, [1747? Dec?] (Box 2, Folder 66)
      1 p. with the grandducal seal, blind
      over red wax, on second leaf.
      New year's greetings.
      Karl Friedrich's portrait attached.
  - CHODOWIECKI, DANIEL, 1726-1801
    - ALS: Berlin, to Anton Graff, 1786 Feb 23 (Box 2, Folder 67)
      1 p.; 17 cm.
      With address and armorial seal.
      Letter of introduction for three
      unnamed young men.
  - CHORLEY, JOHN RUTTER, 1807?-1867
    - ALS: London?, to William MacDowall Tartt, 1833 Jan 31 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      3 p.; 11 x 18 cm.
      Two enclosures: Extracts from
      Goethe's posthumous papers,
      arranged and translated by
      Chorley: I. From a review of
      Carlyle's German Romances, AMs
      (in Chorley's hand), 4 p.
      21 x 26 cm.; II. A notice of the
      Edinburgh & Foreign quarterly
      review, AMs (in Chorley's hand),
  - CHURCHILL, IRVING L.
    - William Shenstone's copy of Macpherson's "Fragments of ancient poetry", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
      13 l.; 28 cm.
      Typescript (original)
      With: Carbon of same typescript
      With: Supplementary notes on
      Shenstone's copy of Macpherson's
      "Fragments of ancient poetry",
      typescript (original), 2 l.; 28 cm.
  - CLARK, LEWIS GAYLORD, 1808-1873
    - ALS: Philadelphia, to Mrs. Townshend Stith, 1835 Jul 5 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      2 p.; 20 x 26 cm.
      On Mrs. Stith's acquaintance with
      Lord Byron.
  - CLAUDY, FRANK, 1844-1919
    - 4 postcards, signed: Washington, D.C., to William Alfred Speck, 1915-18 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Postcards dated: Jun. 24, 1915; Jul.
      20, 1915; Jan. 6, 1916; Jan. 5,
      1918.
      Mostly acknowledgments.
      With: Postcard, signed, from Fred E.
      Woodward to William Alfred Speck.
      1911 Mar 17, Washington, D.C.
      Stating Frank Claudy has not done
      any work on his translation of part
      2 of Goethe's Faust, and does not
      intend to do so.
    - ALS: Washington, D.C., to William Alfred Speck, 1915 Jun 15 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      2 p.; 13 x 20 cm.
      Enclosure: Claudy's English
      translation of Bayard Taylor's poem
      "An Goethe", which was prefixed to
      Taylor's English translation of
      Goethe's Faust. Chiefly in
      reference to Claudy's English
      translation of Goethe's Faust, part
      I.
    - ALS: Washington, D.C., to William Alfred Speck, 1915 Jul 1 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      5 p.; 13 x 20 cm.
      Enclosure: AMs "Zu Bayard Taylor's
      Tod", with typed copy. Discusses
      his translation of Goethe's Faust,
      1. Theil.
    - ALS: Washington, D.C., to William Alfred Speck, 1915 Nov 11 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Discusses William P. Andrews' English
      translation of Goethe's Faust, pt.
      1-2, and G. G. Zerffi's edition of
      the first part of Faust.
    - ALS: Washington, D.C., to William Alfred Speck, 1916 Jan 11 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      1 p.; 20 x 27 cm.
      Mentions Andrews' translation of
      Goethe's Faust; is willing to send
      a copy of Des Voeux' translation of
      Goethe's Torquato Tasso.
    - ALS: Washington, D.C., to William Alfred Speck, 1916 Feb 19 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      Includes t.p. of Claudy's edition of
      Filmore's English translation of
      Goethe's Faust, 1. Theil.
    - ALS, to William Alfred Speck, 1916 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      Claudy discusses his own book
      collection of English translations
      of Faust.
    - 2 ALS: Washington, D.C., to William Alfred Speck, 1916 Jul 14 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      1918 Aug 26
      2 p.; 20 x 24 cm., & 20 x 26 cm.
    - Bayard Taylor, 1899 Oct 29 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      AMs, 8 l.; 35 cm.
      Critique of Taylor's translation of
      Goethe's Faust; includes trans-
      lations of Der König von Thule and
      the spirits' song from the scene
      Studirzimmer by Claudy.
      With an adaptation and continuation
      of Taylor's poem "An Goethe," 5 l.,
      in German.
      Essay and poem were apparently read
      at a sesquicentennial celebration
      of Goethe's birth, given by the
      Washington Sängerbund, 29 Oct 1899.
      Two programs of the celebration laid
      in.
    - Germany, 1905 Feb 25 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      10 numb. l.; 29 cm.
      Typescript (mimeographed copy),
      signed.
      Brief historical sketch and analysis
      of cultural problems.
    - Goethe's Faust, 1899 Jul 26 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      AMs. 35 numb. l.; 27 cm.
  - CLAVICULA SALOMONIS
    Clavicula Salomonis expurgate prit exrat
    im Vaticano assumta. Bibliotheca
    Aeldebergensi: Der König Salomon spricht
    zu seinem Sohn Rabeam. n.d.
    - AMs, 164 p., illus., diagr.; 21 x 17 cm. Caption title. On cover: Clavicula Salmonis ad Filium Rabeam. Text and illustrations, chiefly cabbalistic symbols and diagrams, in red and black and in pencil. The manuscript was written about 1800. Ehrhardt's catalogue note no. 572.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 793
  - COBDEN-SANDERSON, THOMAS JAMES, 1840-1922
    - ALS: Hammersmith W., to Messrs. Maggs Bros., 1910 Feb 8 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      2 p.; 23 cm.
      On stationery of The Doves Press, 15
      Upper Mall Hammersmith W.
      Offering a copy of Goethe's Faust,
      Part II, on vellum.
    - ALS: Hammersmith W., to Messrs. Maggs Bros., 1910 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      2 p.; 23 x 16 cm.
      Letter discusses unavailability of
      Faust I for sale by the Doves Press.
      On stationery of the Doves Press.
  - COGSWELL, JOSEPH GREEN, 1786-1871
    - ALS: Cambridge, to "Dear Sir", 1864 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      1 p.; 20 x 12 cm.
      Letter discusses the authenticity of
      the sketch of a Goethe poem in
      pencil ms.
  - COLERIDGE, SAMUEL TAYLOR, 1772-1834
    - Autograph ms., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 85)
      Perhaps a postscript to a letter.
      Discusses some of Goethe's works.
    - ALS: Highgate, London, to Mr. Boosey, 1816 Aug 31 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      3 p.; 18 x 22 cm.
      About Coleridge's plan to write a
      history of German literature, and
      the request from the Quarterly
      Review to furnish an article on
      Goethe's Dichtung und Wahrheit.
    - ALS, to Boosey & Sons, booksellers, Broad Street, London, [1820?] (Box 2, Folder 87)
      4 p.; 19 cm. with address
      The pages are reinforced with Japan
      paper.
      On the last page written through the
      address, in pencil, a draft of an
      answer by the firm of Boosey & Sons.
      Concerning a proposal for Coleridge to
      write the letter-press for Moritz
      Retzsch's Outlines to Goethe's Faust.
      Printed in Schreiber, Carl F.:
      Coleridge to Boosey - Boosey to
      Coleridge, in Yale University Library
      Gazette, 1947, v. 22, p. 6-10.
  - CONRAD, A.
    - Der Goethe-Enkel. Erlebtes aus Ilmenau, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Typescript (carbon).
  - CONSTANT DE REBECQUE, HENRI BENJAMIN, 1767-1830
    - ALS, to an unknown correspondent, [1809?] (Box 2, Folder 89)
      2 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Removed from Schiller. Wallenstein.
      French tr. Constant de Rebecque
      (Zg18.Sch332.i809).
      Concerning the printing of his
      translation of Schiller's
      Wallenstein.
  - COOKSON, GEOFFREY MONTAGU, B. 1867
    - ALS: Bridport, England, to Dr. A. I. Frantz, 1947 Oct 17 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      1 p.; 20 cm., with envelope
      Stating that he has done no further
      work in translating Faust or any
      other German literature.
      Cookson is the translator of Goethe's
      Faust, part I.
  - COTTA, HEINRICH, 1763-1844
    - ALS: Zillbach, to "Ew. Excellenz", 1806 Oct 3 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      1 p.; 19 x 23 cm.
      The last page of this letter only
      apparently a part of a morphological
      discussion, including the passage:
      "Auch ist [mir] das günstige Urtheil
      des Herrn Geh. von Göthe von hohem
      Werth."
  - COTTA, JOHANN FRIEDRICH, 1764-1832
    Full name: Johann Friedrich Cotta,
    Freiherr von Cottendorf
    - Autograph note to Friedrich von Matthison, 1816 Sep 10 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      1 p.; 21 cm.
      Forwarding a draft in settlement of
      Matthison's account.
      With address on verso of second l.
  - COUDRAY, CLEMENS WENZESLAUS, 1775-1845
    - Receipt, signed: Weimar, to Grossherzogl. Cammer, Weimar, 1820 Jun 15 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      1 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Signed: Coudray
      Printed form, with particulars
      written in.
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Verehrtester Herr College [Leipzig?], 1843 Aug 4 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      3 p.; 16 x 20 cm.
      From 1816 until his death, Coudray
      was an architect at Weimar.
  - COXWELL, CHARLES FILLINGHAM, 1856-1940
    - ALS: Beckenham, Kent, England, to Adolf Ingram Frantz, 1935 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      1 p.; 18 cm., with envelope.
      Submitting a requested
      autobiographical sketch with
      answers to a questionnaire on
      Coxwell's translation of Goethe's
      Enclosure: Autobiographical sketch
      and questionnaire answered.
    - ALS: Beckenham, Kent, England, to Adolf Ingram Frantz, 1935 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      Submitting an addition to the
      autobiographical sketch, sent
      to Frantz on May 6.
  - COXWELL, LOUISE D.
    - ALS: Kent, England, to Adolf I. Frantz, 1947 Oct 20 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      1 p.; 23 cm., with envelope.
      Stating that her husband, Charles
      Fillingham Coxwell, who died in
      1940, has done no further work in
      translating from Goethe.
      Coxwell is the translator of Goethe's
  - CRAVEN, ELIZABETH CRAVEN, BARONESS, 1750-1828
    Full name: Elizabeth (Berkeley), Baroness
    Craven, later Margravine of Ansbach
    - ALS: Londres, to Mr. Peregaux, 1802 Mar 22 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      1 p.; 19 x 22 cm.
      Signed: Elizabeth, M. D'Anspach,
      Bse Berkeley.
      With mention of George Leveson-Gower,
      2d earl of Granville.
  - DALBERG, CHARLES THEODOR ANTON MARIA, 1744-1817
    Title: Baron de Dalberg
    - ALS: Paris, to Philip Albert Stapfer, 1804 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      1 p.; 16 x 21 cm.
      This note brings together in one
      document Stapfer, Villers, and
      Dalberg, who all played an
      important role during the
      Napoleonic period and stood in
      more or less close relation to
      Goethe.
  - DAVIES, MARY, B. 1855
    - ALS: Penybryn, Bangor, N. Wales, to "Dear Sir", 1890 Feb 7 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      "When Sir Charles Hallè first
      produced in this country Berlioz'
      Faust about 79 or 80 with English
      text the chief artists in it were
      Margaret
      Edward Lloyd [etc.] ... Since that
      time I have had the pleasure of
      singing the part of 'Margaret' on
      every occasion on which Sir Charles
      Hallè has given the work ..."
  - DINGWALL, E. G.
    - ALS: British Museum, to Dr. A. I. Frantz, 1947 Mar 15 (Box 2, Folder 101)
      Reply to Frantz' inquiries as to the
      whereabouts of Coxwell, Cookson,
      and Shawcross.
  - DÖBEREINER, JOHANN WOLFGANG, 1780-1849
    - Autograph receipt, signed: Jena, to Herzogliches Rentamt, 1811 Aug 1 (Box 2, Folder 102)
      1 p.; 20 x 15 cm.
  - DON JUAN (PUPPET-PLAY)
    - Don Juan, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 103)
      AMs, 99 p.; 17 x 21 cm.
      Transcribed by Theo Preiske.
      Original puppet-play prompt-book
      written and used by the Saxon
      puppet-player Preiske.
    - Don Juan, 1876-99 (Box 2, Folder 104)
      AMs, signed, 58 numb. l.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Incomplete transcription by Nollmann
      in 1876; completed August 17, 1899
      by F. A. Apel.
    - Don Juan. "Abschrift des Apel- Lorgieschen Don Juan Puppenspieltexts" (Box 2, Folder 105)
      AMs, 40 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Act 1-2 in Ehrhardt's handwriting,
      acts 3-5 in an unknown hand.
    - Don Juan. Lustspiel in 5 Akten [and] Rinaldo, der grösste Räuberhauptmann in Idalien, in 5 Akten. (Box 2, Folder 106)
      AMs, 107 numb. l.; 21 x 17 cm.
      Don Juan: l. 1-50; Rinaldo, l. 51-107.
      Transcribed and signed by Theo
      Preiske.
    - Don Juan; oder, Der steinerne Gast. Schauspiel in 7 Bildern., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 107)
      AMs, 59 numb. l.; 22 x 18 cm.
      Transcriber unknown.
      The Don Juan Ms. ends on verso of
      l. 51; l. 52-59 contain part of
      Genovefa; l. 1, 2, 50, 51 of
      newer paper are written by another
      hand.
  - DORER-EGLOFF, EDWARD, 1807-1864
    - ALS: Baden, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 108)
      1 p.; 21 x 27 cm.
      Dorer-Egloff, Swiss official and
      literary historian, was one of the
      foremost Goethe scholars of his
      time.
  - DURAND, AUGUST, 1790-1852
    - ALS: Weimar, to Karl Gottfried Theodor Winkler, 1836 Sep 2 (Box 3, Folder 109)
      4 p.; 19.5 x 24.5 cm.
      Durand was a celebrated actor in
      Weimar; Winkler, author and
      editor of the Dresdner Abendzeitung,
      was known under the pseud. Theodor
      Hell.
  - EBELING, CHRISTOPH DANIEL, 1741-1817
    - ALS: Hamburg, to Georg Hassel, 1809 Dec 4 (Box 3, Folder 110)
      1 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      With address and red seal.
      Making arrangements for Aaron Burr
      to meet Goethe and Wieland.
  - EBERWEIN, JULIUS
    - ALS: Rudolstadt, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1825 Jul 28 (Box 3, Folder 111)
      3 p.; 18 x 27 cm.
      Author of "Wander-Epigramme", which
      were submitted to Goethe for review
      in "Kunst und Alterthum." Goethe
      does not seem to have kept his
      promise.
    - ALS: Rudolstadt, to Dr. Johann Peter Eckermann, 1836 Jun 8 (Box 3, Folder 112)
      3 p.; 24 x 27 cm.
    - An Eckermann für seine Gespräche mit Göthe, Rudolstadt, 1836 May 22 (Box 3, Folder 113)
      Autograph poem, signed, 2 p.
      23 x 27 cm.
  - EBERWEIN, KARL, 1786-1868
    - ALS: Weimar, to Johann Peter Eckermann, 1845 Aug 11 (Box 3, Folder 114)
      3 p.; 23 x 17 cm.
      Personal brown seal attached.
      Treats of Eberwein's musical
      compositions to "Faust am Hofe
      des Kaisers" from 2d part of
      Goethe's Faust. The music
      apparently has been lost.
    - Autograph receipt: Weimar, to Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, 1812 Apr 19 (Box 3, Folder 115)
      For return by Goethe of music
      material belonging to Eberwein.
  - ECKERMANN, JOHANN PETER, 1792-1854
    - ALS: Weimar, to Dr. Gottlob Regis, 1843 Jan 7 (Box 3, Folder 116)
      1 p.; 21 x 26 cm.
    - ALS: Linden vor Hannover, to C. Scharff, 1845 May 6 (Box 3, Folder 117)
      2 p.; 27 x 22 cm.
      Eckermann acknowledges the return
      of the manuscript of F. J. Soret's
      notes to his supplement to
      Eckermann's edition of Goethe's
      Gespräche mit Eckermann in den
      letzten Jahren seines Lebens, which
      Scharff had found among the papers
      of his late uncle C. T. Musculus.
    - Mit elastischen Armbändern, Weimar, 1825 Jan 21 (Box 3, Folder 118)
      Poem, 1 p.; 25 x 21 cm.
      Printed in J. P. Eckermann, Gedichte,
      1838.
  - EDLING, ALBERT CAJETAN, GRAF VON, D. 1841
    - ALS: Weimar, to Karl Ludwig von Knebel, 1815 Jun 5 (Box 3, Folder 119)
      4 p.; 20 x 23 cm.
      Edling, Hofmarschall, was later
      associated with Goethe in the
      management of the Weimar theatre.
      Except for brief introductory remarks
      and the customary conclusion, the
      letter comprises extracts from a
      letter written by Prince Bernhard
      of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach, dated May
      22, 1815, to Edling concerning
      Knebel's inquiry about officers'
      patents in Dutch regiments.
  - EDUARD, PRINCE OF SAXE-WEIMAR, 1823-1902
    Full name: William Augustus Eduard,
    prince of Saxe-Weimar
    - ALS: Royal Hospital, Dublin, to "My dear Mr. Hamilton", 1889 Mar 18 (Box 3, Folder 120)
      Letterhead: Blue monogram SWE.
      After a long military career in
      Great Britain, Prince Eduard
      became field-marshal in the
      service of Queen Victoria.
      Request to have a dinner engagement
      postponed.
  - EGLOFFSTEIN, JULIE, 1792-1869
    - ALS: Egloffstein, to Christian Jacob Haller von Hallerstein, 1813 Jun 1 (Box 3, Folder 121)
      2 p.; 13 x 18 cm.
      Submitting a drawing to Lessing's
      Emilia Galotti for judgment; the
      drawing is not present.
  - EHRHARDT, GEORG, B. 1862
    - ALS: Dresden, to Richard Bonesky, 1903 May 21
      - 3 p.; 33 cm., folded to 20 cm. Questionnaire with Bonesky's answers in the margin.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, Bound Volumes, folder 803.
    - ALS: Dresden, to Gustav Thorn, 1904 Nov 2
      - 2 p.; 19 cm. Requesting loan of plates to use in publication of Bonesky's Faust text, pub. 1905, and promising a copy of the published book.
      - IN: Faust puppet-play, box 4 folders 153-153a.
    - Doktor Faust, eine Original-Oper in vier Aufzügen vom Doctor Schmieder, in Musik gesetzt von Ignatz Walter, Churfürstlich-Maÿnzischen Hofsänger. 1797, 1901-02 (Box 3, Folder 122)
      AMs, signed, iii, 91, 1 p.; 20 cm.
      Brown board cover.
      Copied 1901/2 by Ehrhardt from a copy
      belonging to Dr. E. Stumme. Note on
      p. 92.
      In verse, without music.
      Based on tragedies by Friedrich
      (Mahler) Müller and Goethe.
      Cf. note on fly leaf.
      Ehrhardt's catalogue no. 2000.
    - Faust, vierter Theil. By C. von Lützow, 1900 Aug (Box 3, Folder 123)
      AMs, signed, 13 l.; 21 x 17 cm.
      In verse.
      Performed for the first time at the
      "Wissenschaftlichen Club zu Wien"
      on March 18, 1879.
      Copied by Ehrhardt from an exemplar
      in the possession of Dr. Emmerich
      von Stumme.
      Ehrhardt's catalogue no. 2315.